Guide to the William E. Irwin Photograph Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William E. Irwin Photographs collection.
1885-1945
WA Photos 516
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.6
(14 boxes)
Photographs of sites and individuals in Oklahoma Territory and Indian Territory, as well as Texas, New Mexico, Arizona, and other places in the American West, circa 1893-1935, chiefly created by William E. Irwin, as well as by his brothers, John Allison Irwin and Marvin Elmore Irwin.
Irwin, William E., 1871-1935
Irwin, John Allison, 1869-1942
Irwin, Marvin Elmore, 1881-1961
Lenny, William J.
Mankins, S. Jack, 1871-1910
Sawyers, William L.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Michael Vinson on the Walter McClintock Memorial Fund, 2011.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
William E. Irwin, Photographs of Kiowa and Comanche Indians (WA Photos 225). Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University.
William E. Irwin (1871-1935)
William Edward "Ed" Irwin (1871-1935) was a photographer active in Indian Territory, Texas, New Mexico, and Arizona, as well as other places in the American West, circa 1893-1935. He was born in Red Oak, Missouri, a son of William Pinkney "Pink" Irwin (1848-1924) and Mary Frances "Molly" Elmore Irwin (1849-1943). He had two brothers who also worked as photographers, John Allison Irwin (1869-1942), and Marvin Elmore Irwin (1881-1961), as well as two sisters, Lou Ida Irwin (1873-1873) and Minnie Pearl Irwin Bock Mitchell Sawyers (1878-1963). Between 1873 and 1878, the Irwin family moved from Missouri to their Buck Horn Ranch near Lometa in Lampasas County, Texas.
Around 1893, Ed Irwin learned photography from J. H. Hurl in Texas, and opened a photography studio in Chickasha, Indian Territory (later Oklahoma). Around 1895, he became partners with S. Jack Mankins (1871-1910), and they operated a photography studio, Irwin & Mankins, also known as the Blue Tent Gallery, in Chickasha until 1903, as well as studios in Duncan, Indian Territory, and Richmond, Texas. In 1903, Ed probably was a partner in the Irwin-Walk Studio in Lampasas, Texas.
In July 1900, Ed married Carrie Matilda "Tillie" Allen Irwin (1878-1922). In 1904, they relocated briefly to Silver City, New Mexico, where they likely continued to own a ranch, and then to Bisbee, Arizona, where Ed operated a studio with his brothers, John and Marvin, until 1922. Marvin also operated a photography studio in Douglas, Arizona, from 1912 to 1945.
In 1922, Ed moved his studio to Douglas, Arizona, probably collaborating with Marvin, and continued to photograph until his death.
Scope and Contents
Photographs of sites and individuals in Oklahoma Territory and Indian Territory, as well as Texas, New Mexico, Arizona, and other sites in the American West, circa 1893-1935, chiefly created by William E. Irwin, as well as by his brothers, John Allison Irwin and Marvin Elmore Irwin.
A significant portion of the collection documents American Indians, including Comanche Indians and Kiowa Indians, in the Oklahoma Territory and Indian Territory, circa 1893 to 1903. These images created by William E. Irwin and his partner S. Jack Mankins that include portraits of individuals, couples, and families, as well as views of settlements and structures. The collection also includes photographs of the territories and American Indians created by William J. Lenny and William L. Sawyers, circa 1889-1891.
Other substantial portions of the collection include landscape views of Texas, New Mexico, and Arizona, as well as hunting parties for deer and fowl in the states, circa 1893-1945. Many of the images include members of the Irwin family or property owned by them, such as the Buck Horn Ranch near Lometa, Texas, owned by William Pinkney "Pink" Irwin. Images of Arizona also include overviews of mining operations, especially in and around Bisbee.
A small portion of the collection documents activities in northern Mexico. These images include deer and puma hunting parties in the Sierra Madre Occidental mountains and Mexican-American Border region in 1907 and 1910. Groups of images relate to the Mexican Revolution, 1910-1913, including the aftermath of the Battle of Naco in April 1913, as well as portraits of Álvaro Obregón Salido and Venustiano Carranza de la Garza. Images of other states in the American West document trips to Alaska, California, Colorado, and Yellowstone National Park.
The collection also includes portraits of the extended Irwin family and friends, as well as a small group of ephemera that documents tax receipts for land in Texas.
The collection includes different photographic presentation methods of the same image, including unmounted and mounted photographic prints, as well as cabinet photographs and photographic postcards. Many discrete images in the collection share the same inscriptions in the negative or on their versos. Additionally, photographers frequently printed images of clouds in landscape views using separate negatives.
Arrangement
Organized into twelve series: I. Alaska, circa 1900. II. Arizona, circa 1904-1945. III. California, 1927-1944. IV. Colorado, circa 1904-1935. V. Mexico, 1907-1913. VI. New Mexico, circa 1904-1935. VII. Oklahoma Territory and Indian Territory, circa 1893-1903. VIII. Portraits of American Indians, circa 1893-1903. IX. Texas, circa 1893-1940. X. Yellowstone National Park, circa 1895-1905. XI. Irwin Family, 1885-circa 1930. XII. Collected Photographs, circa 1889-1940.
Comanche Indians -- Pictorial works; Fowling -- West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Hunting -- West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Portraits; Kiowa Indians -- Pictorial works; Mines and mineral resources -- Arizona -- Pictorial works; Puma hunting -- Mexico -- Pictorial works; Alaska -- Pictorial works; Arizona -- Pictorial works; Bisbee (Ariz.) -- Pictorial works; California -- Pictorial works; Colorado -- Pictorial works; Indian Territory -- Pictorial works; Lometa (Tex.) -- Pictorial works; Mexican-American Border Region -- Pictorial works; Mexico -- Pictorial works; Mexico -- History -- Revolution, 1910-1920 -- Pictorial works; New Mexico -- Pictorial works; Oklahoma -- Pictorial works; Sierra Madre Occidental (Mexico) -- Pictorial works; Texas -- Pictorial works; West (U.S.) -- Pictorial works; Yellowstone National Park -- Pictorial works; Photographic prints; Carranza, Venustiano, 1859-1920 -- Pictorial works; Irwin family; Irwin, John Allison, 1869-1942; Irwin, Marvin Elmore, 1881-1961; Irwin, William E., 1871-1935; Irwin, William Pinkney, 1848-1924; Lenny, William J.; Mankins, S. Jack, 1871-1910; Obregón, Álvaro, 1880-1928 -- Pictorial works; Sawyers, William L.
- Alaska, circa 1900; Series I; 0.21; (1 box)
  Arrangement
  Series I is organized into seven subseries: Anchorage, Chena River, Cordova, Dry Bay, Fairbanks, Seward, and Unidentified Location in Alaska
  Scope and Contents
  This series chiefly consists of landscape views of sites throughout Alaska, as well as sled dog teams, hunting parties, and cabins.
  - Anchorage
    - View of a man with a sled and dog team on a street in Anchorage, Alaska, which includes buildings for the Brown & Hawkins store and Cooper's bakery and café, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Inscription on recto: "Anchorage, Alaska"
    - View of two men with a dog team and sled in a snow-covered forest near Anchorage, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 photographic postcard (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Inscription in negative: "On the trail, near Anchorage, Alaska"
      Inscription on verso: "Dog team in Alaska by WEI"
  - Chena River
    - View of a log structure in a forest, identified as a grub cache, used for storing food, on the Chena River, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Inscription in negative: "The Hunch Creek Cache on the Chena Riv., Alaska. These caches are built for protection of grub against the ever depredating bear. Photo by Irwin"
    - View of a log structure in a forest, identified as a grub cache, used for storing food, near the Chena River, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print and 1 photographic postcard (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Inscription in negatives: "A typical grub cache on the Chena Riv., Alaska, Photo by Irwin"
    - View of two boats on a river, identified as the Chena River, Alaska, near a log building on its bank with two men, circa 1900; 2 unmounted photographic prints and 1 photographic postcard (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Inscription in negatives of an unmounted print and postcard: "Along the Chena Riv., Alaska, Photo by Irwin"
    - View of a boat on a river, identified as the junction of the North Fork and South Fork of the Chena River, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Inscription in negative: "Junction of the north and south forks of the Chena Riv., Alaska, Irwin"
    - View of five men, identified as the Kyle party, in camp on a rocky shore of the Chena River, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Inscription in negative: "Kyle party on the Chena Riv., Alaska, Irwin"
    - Overhead view of a forest and the Chena River in Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Inscription in negative: "Along the upper Chena Riv., Alaska, Irwin"
    - View of the Chena River, Alaska, at midnight, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Inscription in negative: "Along the Chena Riv., Alaska, Photo taken at midnight, Irwin"
    - View of a log cabin on the shore of the Chena River, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Inscription in negative: "Moody's cabin on the Chena Riv., Alaska, Irwin"
    - Exterior portrait of four men, William Edward "Ed" Irwin on left, posed standing, two holding rifles, by the carcass of a caribou on the shore of the Chena River, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Inscription in negative: "Caribou killed at Moody's cabin on the Chena Riv., Alaska, Photo by Irwin"
      Ink stamp on verso: "Irwin's Studio, Silver City, N.M."
    - View of two men posed standing outside a log cabin on the shore of the Chena River, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Inscription in negative: "At Moody's cabin at the mouth of the north fork of the Chena Riv., Alaska, Photo by Irwin"
    - View of a log jam on the Chena River, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Inscription in negative: "Log jam on the Chena Riv., Alaska, Photo by Irwin"
    - View of a rocky shore of the Views along the Chena River, Alaska - rocky river banks, circa 1900; 2 unmounted photographic prints (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Inscription in negative: "Views along the Chena River, Alaska, Photo by Irwin"
    - View of conifer trees on the shore at the junction of the North Fork and Chena Rivers, Alaska, circa 1900; 2 unmounted photographic prints, 1 hand colored (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Inscription in negative of the hand colored print: "Junction of the north fork and main Chena rivers, Alaska, Photo by Irwin"
    - View of five men in camp on a shore of the Chena River, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print, hand colored (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Inscription in negative: "Prospecting party on the Chena Riv., Alaska, Photo by Irwin"
  - Cordova
    - View of trees with a body of water and mountains in the distance, near Cordova, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Inscription in negative: "Views around Cordova, Alaska, Photo by Irwin"
  - Dry Bay
    - View of a ferry boat in dock at Dry Bay, Alaska, with mountains in the distance, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 18)
      Inscription in negative: "Dry Bay, Alaska, Irwin"
  - Fairbanks
    - View of log cabins and a wooden sidewalk in Fairbanks, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Inscription in negative: "On the streets of Fair Banks, Alaska, Irwin"
    - View of buildings at the Agricultural Experiment Station in Fairbanks, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Inscription in negative: "The Government Experiment Farm, Fair Banks, Alaska, Irwin"
    - View of a yak eating from a feedbag at the Agricultural Experiment Station in Fairbanks, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Inscription in negative: "Yak on the Government Farm, Fair Banks, Alaska, Irwin"
  - Seward
    - View of a with a dog team and sled in a snow-covered foothill near Seward, Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print and 1 photographic postcard (Box 1, Folder 22)
      Inscription in negatives: "Dog team near Seward, Alaska"
      Inscription on verso: "Dog train in Alaska, photo by W. E. Irwin"
  - Unidentified Location in Alaska
    - Exterior portrait of two men and a dog team in Alaska, circa 1900; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 1, Folder 23)
      Inscription on recto: "Alaska"
      Inscription on verso: "Scenes in Alaska"
- Arizona, circa 1904-1945; Series II; 1.25; (1 box)
  Series II is organized into thirty-four subseries: Bisbee, Black River, Canyon Lake, Cave Creek Canyon, Chiricahua Mountains, Clifton, Douglas, Fort Thomas, Gila River, Guadalupe Canyon, Kaibab National Forest, Lee's Ferry, Mission San José de Tumacácori, Mission San Xavier del Bac, Morenci, Mormon Flat Dam, Naco, Nogales, O.K. Ranch, Painted Desert, Patagonia, Payson, Ramsey Canyon, Rincon Mountains, Sacramento Hill Mine, Santa Catalina Mountains, Theodore Roosevelt Dam, Tombstone, Tucson, Wellton, Winkelman, Yuma, Unidentified Locations in Arizona (Film Rolls 16 and 24), and Unidentified Locations in Arizona
  This series chiefly consists of landscape views of sites throughout Arizona, as well as images of mining operations, roads, and ranches. Many images depict members of the Irwin family, as well as a few informal portraits of Tohono O'odham Indians.
  - Bisbee
    - View of three donkeys among yucca plants near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Inscription in negative: Views around Bisbee, Arizona
    - View of the Copper Queen Hospital operated by the Copper Queen Mining Company in Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 mounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 25)
      Inscription on recto: "C & A Hospital, Bisbee, Arizona," which probably refers to the Calumet & Arizona Mining Company
    - View of a log cabin near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 2 mounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 26)
      Inscription on the recto of the prints: "A typical mining cabin near Bisbee, Ariz."
    - View of a desert landscape with Fouquieria splendens (ocotillo) cactus and yucca plants near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 3 unmounted photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 27)
      Inscription in negative of two prints: "Views around Bisbee, Ariz., Photo by Ed Irwin"
    - View of a desert landscape with yucca plants near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Inscription in negative: "Typical hillside scenes around Bisbee, Ariz., Photo by Ed Irwin"
    - View of a mining operation, including a smelting plant and tailing pile, near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Inscription on verso: "Views around Bisbee"
    - View of a mining operation, including a smelting plant and railcars from the El Paso and Southwestern Railroad, near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 30)
      Inscription on verso: "Around the mines at Bisbee, Ariz."
    - View of a man with a donkey pack team loaded with ore near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 2 unmounted photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 31)
      Inscription in negative: "Burro pack train loaded with ore, Bisbee, Ariz., Photo by Ed Irwin, Bisbee, Ariz."
    - View of a man with a donkey pack team loaded with ore near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 2 unmounted photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 32)
      Inscription in negative: "Burro pack train packing ore, Bisbee, Ariz., Photo by Ed Irwin, Bisbee, Ariz."
    - View of a man with a donkey pack team loaded with water bags by a water tank near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 33)
      Inscription on verso: "Water train at the loading station, Bisbee, Ariz."
    - View of a man with a donkey pack team loaded with water bags near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 34)
      Inscription on verso: "One of Bisbee's water trains"
    - View of houses on a hill in Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Inscription on verso: "Scenes in Bisbee, Arizona"
    - View of a street in Bisbee, Arizona, including storefronts for a photography studio and the Fair Store, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 36)
      Inscription on verso: "Street scene, downtown Bisbee, Arizona"
    - Overhead view of houses and other buildings in Tombstone Canyon, Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 37)
      Inscription in negative: "Tombstone Canyon, Bisbee, Ariz., Photo by Ed Irwin"
    - View of a mining operation, including a smelting plant and tailing pile, near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 38)
      Inscription on verso: "Views around the mines at Bisbee, Ariz."
    - Interior of Ellis's Flower Shop in Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 39)
      Inscription on verso: "Ellis's Flower Shop in Bisbee"
    - View of three donkeys standing behind yucca plants near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 40)
      Inscription in negative: "Views around Bisbee, Ariz., Photo Ed Irwin"
    - View of a desert landscape with cactus in Arizona near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 41)
      Inscription on verso: "Cactus scenes around Bisbee, Ariz."
    - Exterior portrait a Tohono O'odham Indian woman and two Tohono O'odham Indian children posed among pottery and a brush and cloth shelter near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 2 unmounted photographic prints (Box 2, Folder 42)
      Inscription in negative of a print: "Papago Indian Camp near Bisbee, Ariz., Photo by Ed Irwin"
    - Exterior portrait four Tohono O'odham Indian children, three Tohono O'odham Indian women, and Tohono O'odham Indian man posed standing carrying and among pottery, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 43)
      Inscription in negative of a print: "Papago Indians in their Olla camps near Bisbee, Ariz., Photo by Ed Irwin"
    - Exterior portrait a Tohono O'odham Indian woman posed standing among and holding pottery, as well as a pot on her head, near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 44)
      Inscription on negative of print: "Photo by Irwin"
      Inscription on verso: "Near Bisbee, Ariz."
    - View of a Tohono O'odham Indian man forming a piece of pottery among other unfired pottery, near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - View of Tohono O'odham Indians forming a pieces of pottery among other unfired pottery, near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 46)
      Inscription in negative: "Photo by Irwin"
    - View of a Tohono O'odham Indian monitoring the firing of pottery near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - View of a Tohono O'odham Indian woman and a donkey posed standing among pottery, as well as a pot on her head, near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - View of a woman, identified as Minnie Pearl Irwin Mitchell, posed with a monument in Mule Pass for a road built by prison labor near Bisbee, Arizona, in 1913, 1920 July 31; 1 photographic postcard (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - View of a woman, identified as Minnie Pearl Irwin Mitchell, posed with a monument in Mule Pass for a road built by prison labor near Bisbee, Arizona, in 1913, 1920 July 31; 2 photographic postcards (Box 2, Folder 50)
      Inscription on verso of a postcard: "Monument on top of Divide on Tombstone road, elevation 6400, July 31 - 1920"
      Inscription on recto of a postcard: "Mrs. Mitchell, Arizona"
    - View of a dirt road through the hills near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 51)
      Inscription on recto: "Near Bisbee, Ariz."
    - View of a stone and log structure, identified as the Todd Ranch, near Bisbee, Arizona, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 52)
      Inscription on recto: "Todd Ranch, near Bisbee, Arizona"
    - View of a woman posed sitting on a wooden railing outside an unidentified hotel in Bisbee, Arizona, 1917; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 53)
      Inscription on verso: "Bisbee, 1917"
    - View of mining operations near Bisbee, Arizona, including a smelter and ore railcars for the El Paso and Southwestern Railroad, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - View of mining operations near Bisbee, Arizona, including a smelter and ore railcars, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 55)
      Inscription on verso: "Around the mines at Bisbee"
    - View of the operations of the Copper Queen Mine in Bisbee, Arizona, including its concentrator plant, circa 1904-1922; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 56)
      Inscription on verso: "The C. G. Concentrator Plant, Bisbee, Ariz."
    - View of people walking among debris, including a twisted railroad, in a canyon following a flood, probably in Bisbee, Arizona, 1910 July; 1 photographic postcard (Box 2, Folder 57)
      Correspondence on verso from Carrie Matilda "Tillie" Allen Irwin to Mary Frances "Molly" Elmore Irwin, November 2, 1910
      Postcard missing upper right corner
  - Black River
    - View of the Black River winding through a forest of conifer trees in Arizona, circa 1904-1935; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 58)
      Inscription in negative: "Along Black River, Ariz., Irwin"
    - View of the Black River with fallen logs and a forest of conifer trees in the distance in Arizona, circa 1904-1935; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 59)
      Inscription in negative: "Along the west fork of Black River, Ariz., Irwin"
    - View of the Black River among conifer trees near Springerville, Arizona, circa 1904-1945; 1 photographic postcard (Box 2, Folder 60)
      Inscription in negative: "Along the Black River near Springerville, Ariz., Photo by Irwin"
  - Canyon Lake
    - View of the Canyon Lake reservoir on the Salt River in Arizona, 1929; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 61)
      Inscription in negative: "Canyon Lake along the Apache Trail, Ariz, © by Irwin Bro's 1929"
  - Cave Creek Canyon
    - View of Cave Creek in Cave Creek Canyon, Arizona, with the hat of a man in the foreground, 1920 August 22; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 62)
      Inscription on recto: "Cave Creek Canon, Ariz."
      Inscription on verso: "On Cave Creek, Arizona, Aug. 22, 1920"
    - View of Cave Creek in Cave Creek Canyon, Arizona, with the hat of a man in the foreground, 1920 August 22; 1 unmounted photographic print (Box 2, Folder 63)
      Inscription on verso: "Made in Cave Creek Canon, Aug. 22, 1920"